<noteset subject="shabbos">
  <paragraph context="introduction">
    Although in ruchniyus the relationship is a child – bar/bas mitzva, in aveiros it’s a husband – ba’al aveira. When one does a mitzva, it’s everlasting. A child’s relationship to their parent is everlasting. But the relationship to an aveira can be removed.
    Believe in the goy’s chochma but not in his Torah. In Torah if one gets angry one forgets it but not with chochma. Chochma is external – it doesn’t affect the person inside, but Torah is us, it’s internalised. Goyim can have chochma – but they can’t have Torah that changes and improves their character.
  </paragraph>

  <heading level="1" index="8">הלכות אמירה לאכו"ם – Hilchos amira l’akum</heading>

  <paragraph>
    <list type="LETTER" design="DOUBLEBRACKET">
      <paragraph index="a">
        <heading level="3">The three reasons for this isur</heading>

        <paragraph>
          The Torah writes in Shemos 12:16, כל מלאכה לא יעשה לכם – no melacha shall be done for you – which implies even through a goy, a third party. The Chazal, for various reasons, forbade a Jewish person to instruct a goy to do a melacha which one may  not do oneself on their behalf. The two main reasons for this isur are:

          <list type="NUMBER" design="FULLSTOP">
            <paragraph index="1">
              שלא תיהיה שבת קלה בעיניהם – then Shabbos won’t be taken lightly which could result in performing the melacha oneself on Shabbos.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="2">
              When a goy does the melacha for a yid it’s considered as if the yid has carried out the melacha himself. This is based on the principle of שלוחו של אדם כמוהו, the agent of a person is considered like him. Even though this rule only applies when one Jew asks another to act on their behalf, and the goy isn’t considered an agent of the Jew, nevertheless concerning amira l’akum Chazal were stringent and considered the goy also to be an agent of the Jew, as if the Jew has performed the melacha. Therefore, one may not ask a goy on Shabbos or even before Shabbos to do a melacha for them on Shabbos. This applies whether it’s a melacha min haTorah like cooking or an isur d’rabanon like carrying in a narrow street etc.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="3">
              A further reason is one may not discuss any matters which we are forbidden to do on Shabbos. This is derived from the pasuk – ודבר דבר – discussing which is forbidden. This would include amira l’akum too, that one may not instruct a goy on our behalf to do something that we are forbidden to do on Shabbos. According to this reason it’s also asur to ask a goy to do a melacha after Shabbos because even just talking about such activities is asur. An exception to this third reason is discussions for a mitzva as this wouldn’t be included in ודבר דבר and therefore it’s mutar to instruct a goy on Shabbos to do such a melacha after Shabbos when it’s required for a mitzva since reasons 1 and 2 don’t apply as no melacha is happening on Shabbos.
            </paragraph>
          </list>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="b">
        <heading level="3">Hinting to a goy to perform a melacha on Shabbos</heading>
        <paragraph>
          In the same way as it’s asur to tell a goy to do a melacha for oneself on Shabbos, so too it’s asur to hint to him to do a melacha, even if it wouldn’t involve any talking i.e. by motioning the hands etc. (even showing them a piece of paper with what to do is asur). Therefore one wouldn’t be allowed to say to a goy, ‘Please can you help me as I by mistake left the lights on in the bedroom and we can’t sleep’. Even though one hasn’t asked the goy explicitly to do a melacha, nevertheless since one has asked him positively to help me it’s also considered as a form of request/command. This is known as רמיזה בדרך ציווי – hinting in the form of a command. Similarly even if the goy volunteers on their own accord to switch the light off but asks, ‘Would you like me to switch off the light for you?’ it would be asur to reply, ‘Yes please’ as that is also in fact a command like saying, ‘Yes please, switch off the light’.
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="c">
        <heading level="3">When hinting is mutar</heading>
        <paragraph>
          However, it’s mutar to hint in an indirect manner, i.e. in a passive and non-commanding way, even if the goy will understand what to do. This is known as רמיזה שלא בדרך ציווי – hinting which isn’t in the form of a command, and it’s not included in the isurim of amira l’akum. Therefore if a light was left on in a bedroom, one may hint to a goy that one can’t sleep with the light on. Since one has only mentioned the circumstances, rather than suggesting any practical solution, it’s mutar (provided there’s no isur of benefitting from this melacha as will be explained). Similarly, one may say to the postman when he delivers a letter, ‘I can’t read this letter as I may not open it today,’ from which he will hopefully deduce that he should open the letter. Since no instructions whatsoever have been given to perform any melacha, no isur is involved.
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="d">
        <heading level="3">Having benefit from a melacha carried out by a goy - נהנה ממעשה עכו"ם</heading>
        <paragraph>
          There is an additional isur when a melacha has been performed by a goy not to derive any benefit from the melacha which has been done. Chazal instituted this isur to avoid using a goy on Shabbos and preventing the isur of amira l’akum i.e. instructing a goy to do a melacha for a Jewish person on Shabbos.
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="e">
        <heading level="3">Waiting מוצאי שבת בכדי שיעשו</heading>
        <paragraph>
          The reason for the isur of having benefits from such a melacha is to remove any incentive to ask a goy to do a melacha on Shabbos. Therefore Chazal extended this isur to wait after motzei Shabbos the length of time it would take to carry out that particular melacha. By waiting so long one won’t gain anything by having the melacha done on Shabbos if it could just as well be done after Shabbos. This amount of time is called בכדי שעשו, the time it takes for that melacha to be accomplished. Therefore one may not ask a goy to dry-clean a garment on Shabbos but if one did so i.e. it was brought to the dry cleaners just before the beginning of Shabbos and collected immediately motzei Shabbos leaving no time for the cleaning to have been done except on Shabbos, one wouldn’t be allowed to wear this garment motzei Shabbos for the duration of the time it takes for the cleaning. Similarly, if one would bring a car to a mechanic for repair over Shabbos, in such a way that there is no time for the repair other than during Shabbos, the car may only be used after Shabbos after the time required for the repair has elapsed. This new isur of benefitting from such a melacha applies whether the goy was instructed to do the melacha or was hinted to, or even if the goy carried it out completely on his own accord.
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="f">
        <heading level="3">Which benefits are included in this isur</heading>
        <paragraph>
          Chazal only prohibited to benefit from a melacha performed by a goy on Shabbos where the benefit is positive and newly created e.g. if a goy switches on a light in a totally dark room or if he lit the cooker to cook some food, both of which are considered creating positive direct benefits. This isn’t permitted and a Jew may not benefit from this light at all and may only use the room as if it were dark and similarly in the case of cooking, the food may not be eaten. However when the benefit involved is of an indirect result it’s not asur e.g. if a light was left on in a bedroom and a goy switches it off, either on his own accord or by hinting to him in an indirect manner, the benefit attained is that a disturbing factor has been removed i.e. the light has been switched off, thereby enabling one to sleep as opposed to a positive result when the light is switched on. Similarly, one may hint to a goy to turn off an alarm clock which is ringing, to turn off an oven or a flame, to turn off an iron etc. and to open an envelope, as in all these cases the benefit isn’t from the melacha itself but rather from removing the disturbing and external factors. All such benefits are permitted but one must only hint to the goy indirectly or let him do it of his own accord. Similarly, a freezer which got switched off one may ask a goy indirectly to switch it back on since by doing so one is only keeping a status quo rather than a positive benefit.
          <list type="BULLET">
            <paragraph index="1">
              <heading level="3">An additional benefit</heading>
              If the benefit is only in addition to make the situation, which is already actually possible, a little easier, then that positive benefit is allowed. Only when the positive benefit changes a totally impossible situation to a possibility, is that benefit asur. Therefore if a goy were to switch on an additional light on his own accord or through hinting to it in a room which has sufficient light to read but with difficulty, one may use that light and remain in the room and continue reading even if it’s easier. This is allowed as long as the original lights are still burning but once the original lighting is no longer there one may not remain in that room as one would be having positive benefits from a melacha carried out by a goy. Similarly if there is a heater warming a room one may hint to a goy to switch on another heater as it’s only increasing the temperature heating the room.
            </paragraph>
          </list>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="g">
        <heading level="3">A goy who performs a melacha for his own benefit</heading>
        <paragraph>
          One may only not derive benefit from a melacha when performed by a goy on behalf of a Jew but if the goy carries out the melacha for their own use a Jew may also benefit from it. Therefore if a goy switched on a light in a dark room so that they could find something for themselves one may then ask them to leave the light on so that others could benefit from it. This is permitted since the goy didn’t originally switch on the light for the Jew. Similarly, if a garment was left at the cleaners early enough on Friday that it didn’t have to be cleaned on Shabbos one may benefit from this cleaning immediately after Shabbos even if it may have been cleaned on Shabbos. This is so since the goy wasn’t explicitly asked to do this melacha on Shabbos and he therefore did it on his own accord, for this same reason a goy may wash up with hot water and a sponge since it could have been done with cold water without a sponge, as any melacha which can be done in a permitted way on Shabbos, the goy may do it however they want.
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="h">
        <heading level="3">A goy carrying out work on a Jewish-owned property – מראות העין </heading>
        <paragraph>
          As we have learnt, when a goy performs a melacha for his own personal use, one may derive benefit from it. There is however a situation where a goy may be doing a melacha for their own benefit but the work is being carried out on a Jewish-owned property. This is asur, whether the goy came on his own accord and therefore there’s no amira l’akum, or even if no direct benefit is derived and therefore no נהנה ממעשה עכו"ם, it’s nevertheless still asur. The reason for this asur is that it would appear to the onlooker as if the goy had been instructed by the Jewish person to do the melacha on Shabbos. This is known as מראות העין – as seen by the eye i.e. being suspected of doing something incorrect even though the Jew himself knows that he didn’t give him instructions to work on Shabbos. Therefore when arranging for any work to be carried out it’s vital to stipulate that no work may be done on Shabbos (unless the property is outside the Jewish area and no one knows it belongs to a yid). It’s important to mention the severity of this isur, that Chazal instituted a penalty that such work may never be benefited from e.g. a goy built a house seven days a week and the Jew knew about it and didn’t object – there are opinions that no one may ever live in it. A rav should be consulted if chas v'shalom such a case arises.
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="i">
        <heading level="3">Exceptional cases when amira l'akum is permitted</heading>
        <paragraph>
          <list type="NUMBER" design="FULLSTOP">
            <paragraph index="1">
              <heading level="3">In the case of a choleh</heading>
              when a choleh is concerned, Chazal waived all the halachos concerning amira l’akum, including deriving benefit. One is therefore permitted when necessary to ask a goy to do any melacha, even min haTorah for a choleh. The definition of a choleh in this context includes anyone who would or should go to bed when feeling so unwell e.g. someone with the flu or temperature over 38C/100F or someone whose whole body feels weak and can’t function normally e.g. suffering with a migraine. However minor ailments and discomforts don’t fall into this category. Therefore a person suffering from the flu etc. may ask a goy, even directly, to drive to a chemist, buy some medicine, or phone a doctor for advice and it need not be the choleh themselves, rather anyone can do it for them. Similarly as hospitalised patient may ask, or anyone may ask for them, a non-Jewish nurse/doctor etc. to switch the lights on/off, operate the bed as necessary, to alleviate their condition.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="2">
              <heading level="3">To prevent illness</heading>
              This heter of amira l’akum and having benefit in the case of a choleh as explained, also applies to prevent illness occurring. One is therefore permitted to ask a goy to switch on a heater / to fetch heater / to repair the central heating when it’s very cold, to prevent people becoming ill through the cold – הכל חולים אצל הצינה. This is especially so with regard to children and elderly people who are more sensitive to the cold.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="3">
              <heading level="3">In a case of a mitzva</heading>
              According to most poskim one may not ask a goy to do a melacha even for a mitzva. However the mitzva of bris milah is an exception to this rule due to its great importance. It would therefore be mutar to ask a goy to drive and fetch any paragraph or medicine which would otherwise cause the mitzva to be delayed till after Shabbos.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="4">
              <heading level="3">To avoid a public transgression</heading>
              Similarly, it’s permissible to ask a goy to do a melacha if that would prevent people from committing an aveira. Therefore in such places where people rely on the eiruv and carry, in the event that the eiruv would be broken on Shabbos, it would be mutar to instruct a goy to repair it, so that people wouldn’t be mechalel Shabbos unknowingly.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="5">
              <heading level="3">Cases where the melacha involved is an isur d'rabanon</heading>
              <paragraph>
                This isur of asking a goy to do a melacha applies even to a melacha which is asur mid’rabanon. An isur d’rabanon is referred to as a שבות therefore instructing a goy regarding an isur d’rabanon is known as a שבות דשבות. Although this is generally asur, nevertheless there are certain situations where it would be mutar, being a double shvus, a double d’rabanon, two independent factors each of which is a shvus and one involves a goy.
                <list type="LETTER" design="FULLSTOP">
                  <paragraph index="a">
                    <heading level="3">שבות דשבות במקום הפסד מרובה – to prevent a substantial loss</heading>
                    One would be allowed to ask a goy to remove a very expensive paragraph which is muktzeh to avoid it being stolen or spoilt, e.g. to bring in a camera left outside or a pet escaped from a cage etc.
                  </paragraph>

                  <paragraph index="b">
                    <heading level="3">שבות דשבות במקום מצוה</heading>
                    To fulfil a mitzva one would be allowed to ask a goy to fetch challos from a neighbour’s house with no eiruv, or any basic requirements for Shabbos.
                  </paragraph>

                  <paragraph index="c">
                    <heading level="3">שבות דשבות במקום צער גדול – to relieve a considerable amount of pain</heading>
                    Therefore it would be mutar to ask a goy to fetch a cream etc. from a neighbour or chemist and apply it if one has a painful burn or sting. This would include anything which is kavod habri’os as this is also tza’ar gadol. Since these melachos aren’t asur min haTorah, one may instruct a goy directly to do them in the above cases.
                  </paragraph>

                </list>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>

          </list>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

    </list>

  </paragraph>

  <heading level="1">חורש Ploughing</heading>
  <paragraph>
    <list type="NUMBER" design="DOUBLEBRACKET">

      <paragraph index="1">
        <heading level="3">The definition of חורש</heading>
        <paragraph>
          Choresh means to plough the ground or do anything to soften and prepare the ground for sowing. This can be done in various ways as will be explained.
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="2">
        <heading level="3">Ploughing and softening the ground</heading>
        <paragraph>
          Since in order to prepare the ground for sowing one has to dig and loosen the soil therefore any form of digging, whether with a plough, spade, stick or spoon etc. is included in this melacha. Furthermore this would include any activity of loosening the soil even without the intention of planting. Therefore to drag a heavy chair on soft earth, creating a furrow, is considered choresh and is asur. Similarly to pour water onto the ground which will soften it is also included in this melacha as it cultivates the soil for sowing. Therefore to wash one’s hands over soil even when there’s no intention to plant or sow, since it will inevitably soften the soil, i.e. psik reisha, it’s included in the isur of choresh. (If some plants are already growing, it’s additionally zorei’a.)
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="3">
        <heading level="3">Making grooves/holes in the ground</heading>
        <paragraph>
          <list type="LETTER" design="FULLSTOP">
            <paragraph index="a">
              <heading level="3">Dragging a heavy object on the ground</heading>
              Included in this isur is the creation of any form of hole or furrow of any size as these are suitable for individual seeds to be planted. Consequently,  it’s asur to drag a heavy bench or chair on a surface which will inevitably create a groove. However since this hole has been made in an unusual way, it wouldn’t be asur min haTorah but rather mid’rabanon. Furthermore if there’s no intention to plant it would be mekalkel too. On the other hand, to drag a light chair etc, even though there is a likelihood of creating a hole, since there’s equally a possibility that it won’t occur, it’s considered a דבר שאינו מתכוון, an unintentional melacha, which is permitted.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="b">
              <heading level="3">Dragging a heavy object on a concrete surface</heading>
              It’s not only asur to drag a heavy bench etc. over an earthen surface where it will create a hole, but it’s also asur to do so on a concrete surface eg. in a concrete yard if it would make a hole had it been an earthen surface. Chazal included this even though no hole will occur to avoid this happening to earthen surfaces. However, one may drag such an object across a concrete surface if such surfaces are generally concreted in most houses of the town. Since the majority of houses have these surfaces concreted, Chazal didn’t forbid this activity because of only a minority. Therefore one may drag a heavy bench etc. along a concreted path in front of a house to the gate since nowadays most houses if not all have these paths concreted.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="c">
              <heading level="3">Wheeling a pram or pushchair on the ground</heading>
              <paragraph>
                One is permitted to wheel a pram, wheelchair or buggy on an earthen surface even though the wheels will inevitably cause grooves to appear in the ground. Similarly one may ride a tricycle or scooter even on an earthen surface where grooves will be made. The reason for this is that the isur of choresh only applies when earth is loosened or softened and not when just making a compression on the ground. Please note, to ride a bike on Shabbos is generally not allowed for various reasons:

                <list type="NUMBER" design="FULLSTOP">
                  <paragraph index="1">
                    One could mistakenly go out of the techum
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph index="2">
                    Bikes frequently need repairs and adjusting, involving the melacha of makeh b’patish
                  </paragraph>
                  <paragraph index="3">
                    One could come to carry or wheel it where it’s too hard to ride
                  </paragraph>
                </list>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="d">
              <heading level="3">Making small holes in the ground</heading>
              Since even the smallest hole is sufficient for a seed to be placed inside it, therefore to make any hole in the ground is included in the melacha of choresh and even if there is no intention to plant anything. Therefore to stick a rod or cricket into the ground on Shabbos is asur even if the stick remains in the hole. This is because since a hole has been made it’s considered like a hole with a covering and this stick inside it is the covering. Even though to press the ground isn’t included in the melacha as explained, being the opposite of the melacha, nevertheless since these small holes would protect the seeds it would be included in meleches choresh whereas a wider hole doesn’t protect the seeds and a wind etc. would blow it away.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="e">
              <heading level="3">Removing a stump from the ground</heading>
              If a stump etc. was stuck in the ground from before Shabbos it may be removed i.e. pulled out of the ground on Shabbos although the hole will then be opened up, providing there’s no widening of the hole. Since the hole was already there from before Shabbos and has now only been exposed, it’s not choresh. It’s like removing a lid from a hole on Shabbos which is mutar. However if there’s a possibility that someone will level the ground and fill in the hole, it may not be removed on Shabbos. Therefore in a field where the ground isn’t usually perfectly smooth one may remove a stick from it whereas in a flower garden or well-kept ground one may not.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="f">
              <heading level="3">Making a hole unintentionally</heading>
              Although it’s asur to stick a rod in the ground, if a person requires the help of a walking stick with a pointed tip it may be used even when walking on soil where it would create a hole when placed in the ground as one walks. The same halacha applies when wearing thin high heels or shoes with spikes to prevent one from slipping. The poskim justify this since the hole was made unintentionally – פסיק רישא דלא ניכלא – and it’s l’tzorech Shabbos, the hole is of no advantage, is mekalkel, is being done in an unusual manner – כלאחר יד – and not for it’s usual purpose – אין צריכה לגופה.
            </paragraph>
          </list>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="4">
        <heading level="3">Sand</heading>
        <paragraph>
          There is no isur choresh on very fine dry sand where it’s loose and the hole being dug would have no stability and duration at all. Therefore children may play with sand in a sandpit on Shabbos, provided the sand is dry and loose. Although sand meant for building is generally muktzeh, if it has been designated from before Shabbos for the purpose of children playing with it, it’s not muktzeh but one may not allow children to mix sand with water as this would involve the melacha of losh. Furthermore, if the sand has become moist and therefore any holes would remain for some time, this could involve the melacha of choresh or boneh.
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="5">
        <heading level="3">Improving the ground for planting and sowing</heading>
        <paragraph>
          <list type="LETTER" design="FULLSTOP">
            <paragraph index="a">
              <heading level="3">Removing bricks, wood and weeds</heading>
              Included in the melacha of choresh isn’t only ploughing but any improvement to the ground, making it more suitable for planting. Therefore it’s asur to remove bricks or wood or anything embedded into the ground which would then enable plants to be grown on the ground underneath. Similarly, it’s asur to remove weeds or dead plants as this also improves the ground, enabling other plants to be grown in their place. This, besides being choresh, could also involve zorei’a and kotzer if this would enable other plants to grow. It’s asur to remove the above even in an unusual manner e.g. with one’s foot etc. as to do any melacha in an unusual way is still asur mid’rabanon (obviously, these items would be muktzeh if they hadn’t been set aside from before Shabbos as explained).
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="b">
              <heading level="3">Levelling uneven surfaces</heading>
              To level out is to remove a lump of soil or to fill in any hole is also considered an improvement to the ground, making it more suitable for planting. This is therefore included in the melacha of choresh, known as מַשְוֶה גוּמוֹת – levelling holes. If one plants on uneven ground the plants on the higher ground would be overexposed to the sun and deprived of the rain whereas plants on the lower level would be underexposed to the sun and over-watered, therefore levelling out the ground is essential for good crops to be grown. Even if it’s only done for walking, riding or playing etc, it would be asur not because of meleches choresh being unsuitable to plant, but rather because of building (boneh). This levelling out is an improvement to the surface and is considered a melacha like improving a building or wall etc.
            </paragraph>
          </list>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>

      <paragraph index="6">
        <heading level="3">Activities which can lead to levelling the ground</heading>
        <paragraph>
          Since there are many activities which can lead to levelling the ground, Chazal introduced various precautionary measures to avoid infringing on this isur.
          <list type="LETTER" design="FULLSTOP">
            <paragraph index="a">
              <heading level="3">Scraping mud off shoes</heading>
              It’s asur to scrape the mud off one’s shoes onto earthen surfaces as one may come to do it into a hole in the ground and thereby level it out. However one is allowed to scrape the mud onto a wall or against the edge of a curb or step et.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="b">
              <heading level="3">Scraping dogs' excrement off shoes</heading>
              In a case where one stepped onto such dirt, one may be lenient to scrape it off one’s shoes onto the ground if no wall is available. Obviously, care must be taken not to scrape it off in a place where one will level a hole.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="c">
              <heading level="3">Rubbing saliva or phlegm into the ground</heading>
              It’s asur to rub saliva / phlegm into the ground as this could lead to the levelling of the ground. However one may place one’s foot onto it and press it into the ground without any rubbing movements at all. Furthermore, it’s asur to intentionally walk over such saliva etc. on the ground and press it into the ground whilst walking. Whilst walking, one moves one’s foot in a rubbing manner, backwards and forwards, which can lead to levelling of the ground.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="d">
              <heading level="3">Covering a muddy path</heading>
              It’s asur to cover a muddy path with sand or stones or with any materials which are intended to remain there permanently as this may come to  level the ground which is considered an improvement and included in boneh. Therefore to spread sand on a slippery or icy path to prevent people from slipping would be asur as this is considered an improvement to the ground. If however the sand wouldn’t be left there permanently, it would be mutar. However it’s mutar to spread straw or cardboard over a muddy path, as these don’t normally remain permanently. This must be done with a shinui, i.e. not in the usual weekday manner because of uvdeh d’chol to avoid the possibility of leading to a melacha min haTorah. To achieve this the materials can be placed on a box upside down and then scattering it on the ground. If extremely necessary, it’s  mutar for a goy to spread it normally on behalf of the Yisrael, being shvus d’shvus b’makom tzaar gadol.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="e">
              <heading level="3">Covering dirt on earthen surfaces</heading>
              It’s mutar to cover any dirt/saliva which is lying on a completely level surface with sand/soil even if one has no intention to remove it since this gives no improvement to the surface which is already perfectly level, but rather just covers the unpleasant dirt.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="f">
              <heading level="3">Sprinkling salt on icy or snow-covered paths</heading>
              One may sprinkle salt over such a path since the salt dissolves in the ice or snow, and doesn’t remain on the path to improve it. Furthermore, if one would definitely not leave salt on the path but would eventually sweep it up, there’s no isur in sprinkling it on Shabbos.
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="g">
              <heading level="3">Rolling balls and marbles on Shabbos</heading>
              One may not roll around objects on the ground eg nuts or marbles or golf balls etc, in case one may come to level out the ground to make the game easier. Some poskim also include in the isur playing football since it’s best to play on level ground whereas others say the minhag is to be lenient, especially for children. This isur includes all surfaces, whether earthen or concrete, and even if all such surfaces in the town would be paved. It also includes floor surfaces within a house, whether downstairs or upstairs, which could never be earthen, whether the floors are covered with carpet or vinyl etc. This isur was instituted by Chazal to avoid any confusion between floors which could lead to play on earthen surfaces on Shabbos. However, one may play on a table, mat or blanket which is only a temporary covering, including a loose rug, on the floor. In all these cases there’s no possibility of levelling and one wouldn’t become confused with earthen surfaces. (A game which is meant to be played indoors is not included in this halacha since it’s not meant to be played on earthen surfaces.)
            </paragraph>

            <paragraph index="h">
              <heading level="3">Sweeping floors on Shabbos</heading>
              <paragraph>
                <list type="NUMBER" design="SINGLEBRACKET">
                  <paragraph index="1">
                    <heading level="3">Sweeping earthen surfaces</heading>
                    It’s asur to sweep any earthen surfaces as one may come to level out the ground. Furthermore, some poskim are of the opinion that when sweeping such surfaces it’s not only a possibility, but rather it’s inevitable (psik reisha) that some levelling out will actually occur. This is considered boneh as it is improving the floor.
                  </paragraph>

                  <paragraph index="2">
                    <heading level="3">Sweeping other surfaces</heading>
                    Chazal extended this isur to all surfaces, even when no levelling would occur eg when concrete or covered with tar, to avoid any confusion, provided this type of surface is generally earthen throughout the house. Therefore to sweep the courtyard at the front or back of the house is asur since in most houses they’re not concrete. However, since sweeping floors is considered a necessity needed regularly on Shabbos, this isur wasn’t extended to surfaces which are generally concrete eg a fully concrete path in front of a house or any floors inside the house whether tiled or wooden etc, as such surfaces are generally not earthen and therefore these floors may be swept on Shabbos. If however a path is paved or tiled, and filled with soil between the pavings, it would again be asur to sweep in case one would come to fill in the grooves between the stone etc. Therefore only a fully concreted or tarred path or paved path where the grooves are filled with concrete, would be mutar to be swept on Shabbos.
                  </paragraph>
                </list>
              </paragraph>
            </paragraph>
          </list>
        </paragraph>
      </paragraph>
    </list>
  </paragraph>
</noteset>